Guide to the Witold Gombrowicz Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings by Others About Gombrowicz, 1960-97; Series V; 3.75; (9 boxes)
  - BIBLIOGRAPHY
    - Bibliography by country of publication
      - [Argentina] "Bibliographie des articles polonais en Argentine," typescript annotated, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1043)
      - [Argentina], "Critiques sur Ferdydurke 1947," typescript (photocopy) annotated, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1044)
      - [France], [Articles published in France in 1969-71, 1976], typescript, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1045)
      - [France] "Articles parus sur Yvonne ," typescript, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1046)
      - [France] "Bibliographie des principaux articles français sur Witold Gombrowicz" by RG, typescript carbon, annotated, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 1047)
      - [Germany], [Bibliography of articles published in German press], typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1048)
      - [Great Britain], "Bibliographie des critiques anglaises sur Witold Gombrowicz," by RG, typescript carbon, annotated, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 1049)
      - [Hungary] "Gombrowicz en Hongrie" by Pályi András, typescript, annotated (Box 36, Folder 1050)
      - [Italy] "Bibliographie des principaux articles italienes sur Witold Gombrowicz," by RG, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1051)
      - [Mexico] [ La Palabra y el Hombre, general index for 1957-82, fragment], printed material (Box 36, Folder 1052)
      - [Netherlands] "Bibliographie des principaux articles parus sur Gombrowicz en Hollande" by Paul Beers, typescript annotated (Box 36, Folder 1053)
        See also: Series VI. Commemorative works and activities, Paul Beers, "Interview met Gombrowicz", box 44, folder 1257
      - [Poland] Bibliography, index cards (Box 36, Folder 1054-1056)
      - [Poland] "Artykuly Witolda Gombrowicza drukowane w Kurierze Porannym, Warszawa 1934-38" (Box 36, Folder 1057)
      - [Poland] "Witold Gombrowicz (85 rocznica urodzin - 20 rocznica smierci). Zestawienie bibliograficzne przedmiotowe za lata 1958 w wyborze" by Marta Madej, printed version (photocopy of booklet printed 1989) (Box 36, Folder 1058)
      - [Poland] "Materialy do bibliografii drukow zwartych wydanych poza zasiegiem cenzury w 13 XII 1881-31 XII 1988" by Marek Jastrzebski, printed version, (photocopy of fragment of book published 1994) (Box 36, Folder 1059)
      - [Poland] "Bibliographie de l'oeuvre de Witold Gombrowicz en polonais (Widener Library), Cambridge, Mass.) by RG, typescript (Box 36, Folder 1060)
      - [Sweden] "Artykuly w codziennej prasie szwedzkiej o Gombrowiczu oraz recenzje sztuk", n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1061)
      - [United States] "Bibliographie des critiques U.S.A. sur Witold Gombrowicz," by RG, typescript carbon, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 1062)
      - [Yugoslavia] Notes on editions of WG's works in Yugoslavia, manuscript, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1063)
    - Bibliographies and "tables" of translations
      - "Liste des traductions de l"oeuvre de Witold Gombrowicz" by RG, typescript carbon, annotated, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 1064)
      - "Bibliographie des traductions de l'oeuvre de Witold Gombrowicz" by RG, typescript carbon, annotated, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 1065)
      - "Bibliographie des traductions de l'oeuvre de Witold Gombrowicz" by RG, typescript carbon, annotated, 1975 (Box 37, Folder 1066)
      - "Tableaux 1955-1963 oeuvre de Gombrowicz" by RG, typescript annotated, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1067)
      - "Tableaux des traduction," manuscript, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1068)
      - "Traductions de l'oeuvre de Gombrowicz en langue française", n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1069)
      - "Bibliografia. Witold Gombrowicz - tlumaczenia na jezyki obce," typescript corrected, n.d (Box 37, Folder 1070)
  - ARTICLES
    Arranged alphabetically by author's name
    - Bartoszynski, Kazimierz, " Kosmos i antynomie," printed version, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1071)
      With the dedication note from KB to RG
    - Bloch-Michel, Jean, " Cosmos de Witold Gombrowicz," typescript (photocopy of article of 1966 May 21), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1072)
    - Blonski, Jan, "Gombrowicz a literatura dwudziestolecia," printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1073)
    - Blonski, Jan, "Insaissisable Gombrowicz," printed version, (photocopy, pages missing), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1074)
    - Bondy, François, [First article about WG written after the war in Europe (apart from Poland)], transcript, typescript signed by FB, annotated (Box 37, Folder 1075)
    - Bondy, François, "Witold Gombrowicz ou les duels d'ombre d'un gentilhomme polonais," printed version (photocopy of article from 1966) (Box 37, Folder 1076)
    - Buuren, Maarten Van, "Witold Gombrowicz et la grotesque," 2 printed versions, 1982, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1077)
    - Cataluccio, Francesco, "Gombrowicz e la musica. Considerazioni sul tema della Forma e del Dolore, computer printout, 1993 (Box 37, Folder 1078)
    - Carat, Jacques, "Harold Pinter et W. Gombrowicz," printed version (photocopy of article from 1965), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1079)
    - Chadzynska, Zofia, "Gombrowicz w Argentynie," printed version (photocopy of article from 1962 Apr), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1080)
    - Chylicka, Wanda, "Gombrowicz...?" printed version (photocopy of article of 1971) (Box 37, Folder 1081)
    - Dedecius, Karl, "Witold Gombrowicz oder die totale Parodie," typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1082)
    - Ferreyra, Juan Carlos,"The Gombrowicz affair," in Spanish, typescript, (photocopy of typescript dated 1973 Jun 18) (Box 37, Folder 1083)
    - Glowinski, Michal, "Parodia konstruktywna (O Pornografii Gombrowicza,)" (photocopy of article of 1973), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1084)
    - Goldmann, Lucien, "Le théâtre de Gombrowicz," printed version (photocopy of article from 1970 Jul), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1085)
    - Grenier, Roger, "Witold Gombrowicz: Les Envoûtés, " computer printout, [ca. 1990] (Box 37, Folder 1086)
    - Hartung, Rudolf, "Tagebuch-Notizen (VIII), printed version, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1087)
    - Holum, Solveig, "Yvonne," computer printout, 1997 May 6 (Box 37, Folder 1088)
    - Iwaszkiewicz, Jaroslaw, "Les clefs. La littérature polonaise et l'Italie. Méditations et réflexions sur Szymanowski, Witkiewicz et Gombrowicz," printed version (photocopy of article of 1972), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1089)
    - Iwaszkiewicz, Jaroslaw, "Klucze. Literatura polska i Wlochy. Rozwazania i refleksje o Szymanowskim, Witkiewiczu i Gombrowiczu," printed version, 1987 (Box 37, Folder 1090)
      Translation from French by Tomasz Wójcik; with biographical article on WG by Tomasz Wójcik
    - Jarocki, Jerzy, "Potyczki o slub," printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1091)
    - Jarzebski, Jerzy, "Anatomia Gombrowicza," printed version (photocopy of article from 1972), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1092)
    - Jarzebski, Jerzy, "Opetani. Zapomniana powiesc Witolda Gombrowicza," printed version (photocopy of article from 1972), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1093)
    - Jarzebski, Jerzy, "Pojecie formy u Gombrowicza," printed version (photocopy of article from 1971), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1094)
    - Jarzebski, Jerzy, "Portret Gombrowicza po francusku," printed version (photocopy of article from 1971), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1095)
    - Jelenski, Constantin, "Dalla nudita dei piedi alla nuditá," manuscript (Box 37, Folder 1096)
    - Jelenski Constantin, "De L'histoire à Opérette, typescript corrected (photocopy) (Box 37, Folder 1097)
    - Jelenski, Constantin, "Milosz i Gombrowicz," printed version (photocopy of article from 1978), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1098)
    - Jelenski, Constantin, "Notes pour un project théâtral issu de L'Histoire de W.G.," typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1099)
    - Jelenski, Constantin, draft, in French, manuscript (Box 37, Folder 1100)
    - Kijowski, Andrzej, "Kategorie Gombrowicza," printed version (photocopy of article from 1971) (Box 37, Folder 1101)
    - Kliemann, Peter, "Die Romane von Gombrowicz," printed version
      - Printed version, 1964 (Box 37, Folder 1102)
      - Printed version annotated by WG, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1103)
    - Kott, Jan, "Polska diaspora," printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1104)
    - Kozimor, André, "Gombrowicz, la Polonité et l'absurde dans Trans-Atlantique ," printed version, 1984 (Box 37, Folder 1105)
    - Krysinski, Wladimir, "Modus imitandi," printed version, 1984 (Box 37, Folder 1106)
      With dedication note from WK to RG
    - Krysinski, Wladimir, "Pirandello et Gombrowicz. Deux visions de l'homme inauthentique", printed version, (photocopy of article from 1973 Sep) (Box 37, Folder 1107)
    - Kucharski, Allen, "Poland's impossible Avant-Garde," computer printout, 1995 May (Box 37, Folder 1108)
    - Maciag, Wlodzimierz, fragment, printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 1109)
    - Malic, Zdravko, "Le construction du Trans-Atlantique de Witold Gombrowicz," printed version, 1971 (Box 37, Folder 1110)
    - Marchesani, Pietro, "Il bestseller di Gombrowicz, ovvero,'un romanzo per le cuoche'," typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1111)
    - Morawiec, Elzbieta, [untitled, 1st page missing], printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1112)
    - Morawski, Stefan, "Egzystencjalizm oswojony," printed version (photocopy of article from 1973 Jun), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1113)
    - Nakov, Andréi B., "Gombrowicz et Dubuffet. A la recherche du paradis a-culturel (Box 38, Folder 1114)
      With dedication note from ABN to RG (annotation)
    - Nelson, Victoria, "The New Science of Witold Gombrowicz," printed version, (photocopy from article of 1990), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1115)
    - Pasierb, Janusz St., fragment of Galezie i liscie, [book published in 1985], printed material (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1116)
    - Pasolini, Pier Paolo, "Witold Gombrowicz, Journal 1957-1961", printed version (photocopy of an article from 1972), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1117)
    - Przychodzien, Janusz and Grondal, Ewa, [untitled], typescript corrected (Box 38, Folder 1118)
    - Quebrado, Marcos de, "Gombrowicz podsluchany," printed version (photocopy of articles of 1973), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1119)
    - Regnault, François, "Optique de Gombrowicz," printed version (photocopy of article from 1969), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1120)
    - Rússovich, Alejandro, "La semiótica. Intersección entre la naturaleza y la cultura," computer printout, 1997 (Box 38, Folder 1121)
    - Rússovich, Alejandro, "La visión cósmica de Gombrowicz," computer printout, [1997] (Box 38, Folder 1122)
      Includes Polish translation "Gombrowiczowska wizja kosmosu" by Agnieszka Flisek
    - Sadowska-Guillon, Irène, "La mise en scène d'une vie. Le théâtre et ses fonctions dans l'oeuvre de Witold Gombrowicz," printed version, 1984 (Box 38, Folder 1123)
    - Sadowska-Guillon, Irène "La trahison de langage. Le Mariage de Witold Gombrowicz," printed version (Box 38, Folder 1124)
    - Sadowska-Guillon, Irène, "Le théâtre subversive de Witold Gombrowicz," printed version (photocopy of article of 1989 Dec), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1125)
    - Sadowska-Guillon, Irène, "Un freudisme cousu d'enfant," printed version, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1126)
    - Salgas, Jean Pierre, "Urgence de Gombrowicz," printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1127)
    - Sandauer, Artur, "Witold Gombrowicz: l'homme et l'écrivain," printed version (photocopy) (Box 38, Folder 1128)
    - Schindlbeck, Michael, "Witold Gombrowicz: Les Envoûtés - Die Besessenen " [critique for editor], typescript (photocopy), annotated (Box 38, Folder 1129)
    - Swieczewski Karol [?], fragments, typescript, manuscript (photocopy), n.d (Box 38, Folder 1130)
    - Szpakowska, Malgorzata, "Gombrowicz - teoretyk sztuki," printed wersion, (photocopy of article from 1972), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1131)
    - Sztejnberg, Suzy, "la Pornographie ou la réalisation du néant," typescript (Box 38, Folder 1132)
      Includes a letter to RG
    - Tarnawski, Wit, "Od Gombrowicza do Mackiewicza," printed version (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1133)
      Contains chapters of book published by: London, Oficyna Poetow i Malarzy, 1980
    - Tatarkiewicz, Anna, "Anty-wieszcz i jego prorok," printed version, (photocopy of article from 1972 Jul-Aug), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1134)
    - Wyskiel, Wojciech, "Mysli rózne o Gombrowiczu," printed version (photocopy of article from 1972), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1135)
    - Wyskiel, Wojciech, "O Trans-Atlantyku Witolda Gombrowicza," printed version (photocopy of article from 1973 J ul-Aug), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1136)
    - Zaczykiewicz, Bartosz, "'...podszyty!' wariacje na temat przedstawienia na motywach Ferdydurke Witolda Gombrowicza" [performance reviews], computer printout, [aft. 1994] (Box 38, Folder 1137)
    - Unidentified, "Teatr marjonetek Witolda Gombrowicza. (O powiesci Transatlantyk )" transcript, typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1138)
    - Unidentified, "Gombrowicz's Cosmos: the Clinical Fiction as Novel, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1139)
  - BIOGRAPHICAL ARTICLES AND NOTES
    - Biographical note, fragment of published book, in Polish, (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1140)
    - Biographical note, fragment of Slownik wspólczesnych pisarzy polskich edited by Ewa Korzeniewska, Warszawa 1963 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1141)
    - Biographical note, fragment of Wspólczesni polscy pisarze i badacze literatury edited by Jadwiga Czachowska and Alicja Szalagan (photocopy) (Box 38, Folder 1142)
    - Biographical note, printout from the Internet website, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1143)
    - Fragment of Contemporary Literary Criticism, Vol.49 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1144)
    - Thompson, Ewa M., "Chapter One. In Place of a Biography," typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1145)
  - TRANSCRIPTS OF RADIO BROADCASTS
    Arranged alphabetically by the name of the broadcast company. The date provided is the date of transmission.
    - Bayerischer Rundfunk
      - "Von neuen Büchern" by Ute Stempel, typescript, 1984 Jan 18 (Box 38, Folder 1146)
        Includes discussion on Ferdydurke
      - "Bücher - ein Magazin für Leser," typescript, 1989 Jan 21 (Box 38, Folder 1147)
        Contains text about Dziennik 1953-69
      - "Für Sie gelesen - Aus neuen Büchern," typescript annotated by WG, 1966 (Box 38, Folder 1148)
        Includes discussion on Kosmos
      - "Für Sie gelesen - Aus neuen Büchern," typescript annotated by WG, 1963 (Box 38, Folder 1149)
        Includes discussion on Pornografia
    - Deutsche Welle
      - " Bacacay - Witold Gombrovicz [sic]," in Rumanian, typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 1150)
    - Deutschlandfunk
      - "Alle Peinlichkeit der Welt. Zum 20. Todestag des polnischen Schriftellers Witold Gombrowicz" by Helmar Harald Fischer, typescript, 1989 Jul 20 (Box 39, Folder 1151)
      - "Bücher in Gespräch. Witold Gombrowicz: Die Besessenen. Roman," typescript, 1989 Apr 23 (Box 39, Folder 1152)
      - "Bücher in Gespräch. Witold Gombrowicz. Ferdydurke ," typescript corrected, (photocopy), 1984 Feb 5 (Box 39, Folder 1153)
      - "Bücher in Gespräch. Witold Gombrowicz: Indizien. Roman" [review by Peter Klieman], typescript annotated by WG, 1966 May 22 (Box 39, Folder 1154)
      - "Bücher in Gespräch. Witold Gombrowicz: Tagesbuch ." [review by Jürgen Manthey], typescript, 1989 Jan 1 (Box 39, Folder 1155)
      - "Bücher in Gespräch. Witold Gombrowicz: Transatlantik. Roman"[review by Peter Klieman], typescript, 1989 Jan 5 (Box 39, Folder 1156)
      - "Mit fremden Augen" (71st program of series "Klopfzeichen. Gedanken von Rolf Schroers"; review of Berliner Notizen ), typescript carbon annotated by WG, 1966 May 17 (Box 39, Folder 1157)
      - "Schriftsteller unserer Zeit. Witold Gombrowicz porträtiert von Rudolf Hartung," typescript annotated by WG, 1966 Mar 3 (Box 39, Folder 1158)
    - Hessischer Rundfunk
      - "Die Alternative - Kultur am Vormittag," (Hans Peter Koopmann's review of Ferdydurke ], typescript corrected (photocopy), 1984 Aug 1 (Box 39, Folder 1159)
      - "Die Alternative - Kultur am Vormittag," (Jochen Köhler's review of Kosmos ), typescript corrected (photocopy), 1985 Aug 18 (Box 39, Folder 1160)
      - "Die Alternative - Kultur am Vormittag," [Christian Göldenboog's review of Polnische Erinnerungen ], typescript corrected (photocopy), 1986 Mar 3 (Box 39, Folder 1161)
      - "Das Buch der Woche. Witold Gombrowicz: Berliner Notizen. Besprochen von Rudolf Hartung," typescript, 1966 Jan 16 (Box 39, Folder 1162)
      - "Das Buch der Woche. Withold [sic] Gombrowicz Ferdydurke besprochen von Marcel Reich-Ranicki," typescript, 1960 Nov 6 (Box 39, Folder 1163)
      - "Das Buch der Woche. Witold Gombrowicz: Indizien Roman. Besprochen by Rudolf Hartung," typescript annotated by WG, 1966 (Box 39, Folder 1164)
      - "Das Buch der Woche. Witold Gombrowicz: Verführung. Roman. Besprochen by Rudolf Hartung," typescript, 4 copies, one annotated by WG, 1963 Oct 6 (Box 39, Folder 1165)
      - "Stichworter bei meiner Lektüre" (Ernst Kreuder's review of Dziennik ), transcript, 1968 Apr 12 (Box 39, Folder 1166)
    - Norddeutscher Rundfunk
      - "Bibliothek/Zum Lesen empfohlen. Witold Gombrowicz: Ferdydurke. Roman," typescript, 1984 Feb 17 (Box 39, Folder 1167)
      - "Ein Buch meiner Wahl. Witold Gombrowicz: Verführung mit einer Einführung von François Bondy," typescript corrected annotated, 1964 Feb 16 (Box 39, Folder 1168)
      - "Das literarische Portrait. Witold Gombrowicz" [program by Jürgen Manthey], typescript, 1962 Apr 10 (Box 39, Folder 1169)
      - "Neue Bücher. Kosmos. Roman von Witold Gombrowicz. Besprochen von Matthias Brand, typescript (photocopy), 1985 Jul 8 (Box 39, Folder 1170)
      - "Paris entdeckt einen polnischen Autor: Witold Gombrowicz," typescript corrected (photocopy), 1990 Jan 1 (Box 39, Folder 1171)
      - "Witold Gombrowicz: Bacacay. Erzählungen" [reviewed by Matthias Brand, typescript corrected (photocopy), 1984 Aug 27 (Box 39, Folder 1172)
      - "Zum Lesen empfohlen. Die Besessenen. Roman von Witold Gombrowicz," typescript (2 copies), 1989 Aug 14 (Box 39, Folder 1173)
        Includes fragment of German translation of Opetani.
      - "Zum Lesen empfohlen. Witold Gombrowicz Tagesbuch 1953-1969, print, 1989 Feb 10 (Box 39, Folder 1174)
      - "Zum Lesen empfohlen. Witold Gombrowicz Transatlantik ," print, 1987 May 15 (Box 39, Folder 1175)
      - "Zum Lesen empfohlen. Witold Gombrowicz Polnische Erinnerungen ," print, 1985 Nov 1 (Box 39, Folder 1176)
        Includes a fragment of German translation of Wspomnienia polskie
    - Österreichischer Rundfunk
      - Review of Die Besessenen in series "Ex Libris," typescript corrected (photocopy), 1989 Jul 23 (Box 39, Folder 1177)
      - "Literaturmagazin," (review of Pornografia ), typescript (photocopy), 1985 Sep 2 (Box 39, Folder 1178)
      - Review of Dziennik in series "Ex Libris," typescript corrected (photocopy), 1989 Feb 2 (Box 39, Folder 1179)
      - Österreichischer Rundfunk, (review of Kosmos by Cornelia Krauss's in series "Ex Libris"), typescript corrected (photocopy, 2 copies), 1985 Jun 10 (Box 39, Folder 1180)
      - Review of Polnische Erinnerungen by Cornelia Krauss in series "Ex Libris," typescript corected (photocopy), 1985 Jun 10 (Box 39, Folder 1181)
      - Review of Trans-Atlantik by Cornelia Krauss in series "Ex Libris," typescript corrected (photocopy), 1987 Apr 10 (Box 39, Folder 1182)
      - "Du Treuer Hund meiner Seele. Das Tagebuch des Witold Gombrowicz" [review by Gundl Nagl], typescript carbon, annotated by WG, 1966 Jun 25 (Box 39, Folder 1183)
    - Radio 100
      - "Immer in die Fresse. Ein Abend mit Witold Gombrowicz," typescript, 1989 Apr 26 (Box 39, Folder 1184)
    - Radio Bremen
      - "Begegnung mit einem Buch. Witold Gombrowicz: Indizien. Roman," typescript (photocopy), annotated, 1966 Nov 11 (Box 39, Folder 1185)
      - "Neues vom Büchermarkt," ( Berliner Notizen and Indizien ), typescript, 1966 May 12 (Box 39, Folder 1186)
      - "Neues vom Büchermarkt," Gespräche ], typescript carbon annotated by WG, 1969 Apr 24 (Box 39, Folder 1187)
      - Radio program, print, 1970 Dec 10 (Box 39, Folder 1188)
    - Radio Free Europe
      - "Gombrowicz's Defense" by Constantin Jelenski, typescript annotated, manuscript (photocopy), 1963 Oct 22 (Box 40, Folder 1189)
      - "The Best Polish Book in Exile 1945-1975," in Polish, typescript corrected (photocopy), 1975 Apr 6 (Box 40, Folder 1190)
    - Rundfunk in Amerikanischen Sektor
      - " Die Trauung von Witold Gombrowicz in deutscher Sprache Schiller-Theater" by Horst Eifler, typescript (photocopy), 1968 Jan 10 (Box 40, Folder 1191)
      - "Von Büchern und Scriftellern" by Paul Schallück, Wilhelm Höck, Maria Peti, Helmut Uhlig, Jens O. Luther, typescript, 1966 Oct 24 (Box 40, Folder 1192)
      - "Witold Gobrowicz: Tagebuch 1953-1969 vorgestellt von Sigrid Herzog", 1989 Apr 4 (Box 40, Folder 1193)
    - Sender Freies Berlin
      - "Buchzeit. Witold Gombrowicz: Bacacay. Erzählungen," [reviewed by Jürgen Manthey], typescript, corrected (photocopy), 1984 (Box 40, Folder 1194)
      - "Buchzeit. Witold Gombrowicz: Berliner Notizen ," typescript annotated by WG, 1966 Jan 22 (Box 40, Folder 1195)
      - "Buchzeit. Witold Gombrowicz: Die Besessenen ," typescript, 1989 Jul 31 (Box 40, Folder 1196)
      - "Buchzeit. Witold Gombrowicz: Gesammelte Werke in dreizehn Bänden. Band 1 Ferdydurke '," (reviewed by Jürgen Manthe) typescript, 1984 Mar 14 (Box 40, Folder 1197)
      - "Buchzeit. Witold Gombrowicz: Kosmos. Roman." (Reviewed by Jürgen Manthey), typescript corrected (photocopy), 1985 Aug 26 (Box 40, Folder 1198)
      - "Ein Leser gibt Auskunft" (review of Opetani by Rudolf Hartung), typescript, 1964 Feb 28 (Box 40, Folder 1199)
      - "Buchzeit. Witold Gombrowicz: Polnische Erinnerungen ." (Reviewed by Jürgen Manthey), typescript corrected (photocopy), 1986 Mar 17 (Box 40, Folder 1200)
    - Süddeutscher Rundfunk
      - "Ein Buch und eine Meinung. Günther Oliass spricht über den Roman Ferdydurke " von Witold Gombrowicz, typescript, 1961 Jan 26 (Box 40, Folder 1201)
      - "Ein Buch und eine Meinung. Günther Oliass spricht über Das Tagebuch " des Witold Gombrowicz, typescript, 1962 Jul 19 (Box 40, Folder 1202)
      - Radio program about Opetani, 1989 Mar 22 (Box 40, Folder 1203)
      - "Tagebuch für Leser," print, 1969 Sep 29 (Box 40, Folder 1204)
        Includes Martin Gregor Dellin's review of Gespräche
      - "Zwischen-Töne," [fragment of Kosmos ], typescript (photocopy), 1985 Jul 17 (Box 40, Folder 1205)
      - "Zwischen-Töne," [fragment of Trans-Atlantik ], typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 40, Folder 1206)
      - "Zwischen-Töne," [fragment of Polnische Erinnerungen, typescript (photocopy), 1986 Mar 7 (Box 40, Folder 1207)
    - Südwestfunk (Baden-Baden, Germany)
      - "Das Buch der Woche. Witold Gombrowicz: Indizien, typescript annotated by WG, 1966 Sep 17 (Box 40, Folder 1208)
      - "Das Buch der Woche. Witold Gombrowicz: Trans-Atlantik," typescript annotated by WG, 1965 Jan 10? (Box 40, Folder 1209)
      - "Das Buch der Woche. Witold Gombrowicz: Verführung ," typescript, 1964 Mar 22 (Box 40, Folder 1210)
      - "Soirée neue Bücher/neue Texte. Witold Gombrowicz: Bacacay: Erzählungen," typescript (photocopy), 1984 Aug 18 (Box 40, Folder 1211)
    - Westdeutscher Rundfunk
      - "Das Buch, das uns auffiel. Das Tagebuch des Witold Gombrowicz" (program by Paul Schallück), typescript annotated, 1962 Jul 23 (Box 40, Folder 1211a)
      - "Ein Buch in unserer Zeit. Verführung Witold Gombrowicz," typescript, 1964 Apr 14 (Box 40, Folder 1212)
      - "Buchkritik. Witold Gombrowicz: Trans-Atlantyk, Indizien, Berliner Notizen, Aus dem Tagebuch, print, 1966 May 31 (Box 40, Folder 1213)
      - "Meinungen über Bücher. Witold Gombrowicz: Polnische Erinnerungen " (reviewed by Jürgen Menthey), typescript (photocopy), 1986 Mar 4 (Box 40, Folder 1214)